Thank you.
Assalamu alaikum.
How are you?
Alhamdulillah.
Our book is Ad-Da'u wa al-Dawa' that describes also rifa' to us.
Ad-Da'u wa al-Dawa' was compiled by Al-Imam Ibn al-Qayyim,
as a response to someone who had asked him a question.
This man had approached the Imam, he expressed his condition to the Imam,
he sought a response for what he was in,
because it became so clear that this individual was in a big, big trouble.
He said, the Imam mentioned what this individual said,
What is it that the leading scholars,
What have they said?
The leaders upon the path of the Deen, the scholars,
He said,
What have the heads, the leading scholars amongst the ulama,
What have they said regarding a man,
He was afflicted by a trial, by an affliction,
And this individual clearly knows for certainty,
That if that trouble and affliction continues with him,
This affliction,
It will destroy his dunya, it will destroy his akhirah.
The man understood, if I continue like this,
Life will be bad.
And this man had made a lot of efforts to put away this evil,
this bad behaviour, this bad character,
this sinful life of unrighteousness that he fell into.
He had tried to put it away by all means that he knew.
But as he tried the efforts that he knew,
This thing,
This baliyah was increasing, the affliction, it was worsening,
It got worsened,
in its intensity,
and strength.
What is the way out to put this matter away from myself?
What is the path that I will follow,
so that I can remove this evil from myself?
May Allah shower his mercy and compassion upon whomever becomes merciful,
and provides support to a person that is in an affliction.
Then he cited the hadith to encourage the Prophet Muhammad,
to encourage us, he cited the hadith of the Prophet Muhammad,
so that the scholar is encouraged to answer.
It was not like many do these days.
They want to bully ustaz to answer.
They want to bully sheikh to answer.
So they began to agitate, no.
Encourage him to answer, he may have a lot of issues grappling with.
So he reminded the sheikh,
Sheikh, the way you support,
and will provide support to a servant,
for as long as the servant is upon providing help and support to his brother.
Sheikh, help me.
If you help me and support me, Allah will help you and support you.
Please grant me, provide me the religious willing on this matter.
And as you do so, may Allah reward you abundantly.
May Allah be pleased and show his compassion towards you.
May Allah be pleased with you.
May Allah make us all and you the Imam that I am asking this question.
May Allah grant us ends that are of benefit and goodness to us.
This was his question.
He was in trouble, he was in a worry.
Some of the scholars said he was in a trouble of regularly committing zina.
Some say it was pornography, some say different things the scholars have mentioned.
What the man said regarding himself was he was in an addictive trouble on righteousness.
And that will bring destruction.
No doubt, may Allah protect all of us.
So the Imam Rahimullah Ibn al-Qayyim began to assure him that Allah will bring you out of this condition.
Many times people get into conditions, they become confused, they become worried.
So sometimes the first thing to straighten up in them is that they should be hopeful that Allah will remove them from this evil.
This hope, that Allah will remove me and begin to make efforts to get out of this trouble in the ways that the ulema will suggest.
And we have been reading in this book that is from the aspects of Husnu Zonni Billah, Allah will help me.
Allah will provide support for me out of his mercy.
So I will begin the process of tawbah, all what he had done in the past.
If the tawbah is genuine, if the tawbah is sincere, Allah will provide me help.
He will pardon me if I repent genuinely.
Unfortunately, some of the people continue to remain up on sin, thinking that they are hoping positively in Allah.
If the hope with Allah is positive, then we must begin to take steps out of sin, if your hope, if your anticipation of goodness with Allah is genuine.
That is known by the individuals taking steps out of the old ways.
Imam Ibn al-Qayyim said,
There is no doubt that a person is thinking positively, anticipating goodness and beneficence from Allah.
You find it and it actually occurs when you are doing what is right.
If a person is doing what is right, what does he expect? Good rewards.
He said,
Because this one who is thinking and hoping for goodness from Allah.
The Imam said,
He definitely hopes in goodness in Allah, that Allah will give him good rewards, Allah will give me good recompense.
And Allah does not break his promise.
He promises, if you observe Salah, I will be kind to you. If you pay Zakat, I reward you.
You make dua, I will accept.
The one who is not making dua is waiting for goodness. You did not ask for anything.
The one who is up on Zina is hoping for goodness. You are up on sinfulness.
So the Imam said,
The one who is hoping for goodness is so doing because he anticipates goodness, good rewards for what he has done.
He said,
And Allah does not break his promise.
If I repent and I am repenting, Allah accepts repentance.
And really this thing really comes to mind.
If something happens and the individual regrets, why did I do this?
As you carry on that mindset of regret and never to proceed, it begins to come to your mind that Allah accepts it.
You have one reverse calmness in your mind regarding Tawbah.
So he said,
But as for the one who is al-Musi' is regularly upon evil practices.
He is always upon major sins.
Today he drinks alcohol. Tomorrow he comes to Zina.
Next tomorrow he is up on gambling.
The other day he is up on telling a lie to deceive the people to collect the money from them.
Or zulm, being unjust to people.
Walmukhalafat and other deeds of disobedience to Allah.
Where will he find being positive and anticipating goodness?
Will he even have time to think that Allah will show a mercy upon him?
So Imam al-Hasan al-Basri was cited.
Ibn al-Qayyim cited Imam al-Hasan al-Basri who said,
The people of the person of Iman,
He was hopeful in the mercy of Allah.
He was looking for rewards from Allah.
He was looking for goodness with Allah.
He was looking for tranquility and good mind from Allah.
Allah grant me this. Allah grant me this.
That Mu'min, he therefore made his deeds to be good.
I want good from Allah. Let me use good deeds.
I want protection from Allah. Let me make Salat.
I want progress. I want goodness for my children.
Let me make haste towards that.
The person of Iman,
He hopes for goodness from his Lord.
So he makes his good to be good.
Why? He is expecting goodness from Allah.
As for the criminal,
He is not thinking. He is thinking about Allah is not positive.
So his deeds are bad.
Bad deeds make you think evil about Allah.
But it would be unfortunate if the individual is upon evil deeds.
He is now expecting good rewards.
Ibn al-Qayyim went to cite about 38 ahadith.
To say that, like he called it, that it is part of al-hamaka.
A person is being stupid.
To be upon evil deeds.
He drinks alcohol.
He gambles.
He is upon riba.
He is upon zina.
He tells lies. He deceives.
He is arrogant towards his parents.
He delays Salah and observes Salah just when he likes.
And he refuses perhaps to observe zakah.
He has the money, he will not go for hajj.
And then in all of these,
when he is encouraged, Mektub says,
No, we are hoping for goodness from Allah.
Upon sinfulness,
the ulamas say this is hamaka.
It is stupidity.
It does not make sense.
It is opposite intelligence.
That the deeds of the prophets call it that.
It refers to such persons as al-ajizu.
He said alayhi salatu was salam.
He said, al-ajiz,
the one who is far from being sensible,
is that person whose deeds are bad.
The prophet said alayhi salatu was salam.
So al-ajiz,
the one whose deeds are far from being sensible,
at all.
The deeds are bad.
He commits sin.
He is not, his deeds are not,
they are not in line with goodness.
He makes his soul to follow just whatever he desires.
Whatever he desires, just do it.
When he follows his desires,
he is now still expecting Allah for goodness.
Upon following your desires.
Upon all this sinfulness.
Tamanna ala Allah.
He is still waiting for Allah.
Allah, do good to me.
Allah, give me money.
Upon shirk.
Upon sehir.
Upon going to churches as a Muslim.
Is this saying Allah will help me?
No, you have to stop that.
So al-Imam rahimahullah mentioned about 38 ahadith.
To make us understand that,
evil deeds are followed by evil repercussions.
And good deeds are followed by goodness.
If you are upon good deeds,
if a person is upon sin,
he begins to anticipate khairat, barakat.
The day he starts tawbah.
He will feel it by himself.
I have turned a new leaf.
And I know somebody who was like that.
He used to be on drugs.
He is late now.
He used to have people.
He would be in bus stops, pickpockets.
All of this.
Their house is just about 5 or 6 houses away from us.
And his father was well known.
This boy just turned one day.
He observed salah.
He went to the masjid.
The masjid where if he came,
everybody was afraid what he came to do.
He made wudu, two units of prayer.
Just like that.
This boy turned.
Muhammad was his name.
He turned.
He began upon good deeds.
So that time, everybody who saw him,
they said,
We are looking calm now.
We are looking honorable.
We are looking this.
One of the men in the masjid volunteered
to provide him his daughter for marriage.
But you know what, ikhwa?
This man did not stay long till he died.
Just like the prophet had told us,
alayhi salatu wa salam,
about the one,
Inna ahadakum la ya amalu bi amali ahali naar.
The individual will be upon the deeds
of the people of Jahannam.
Hatta ma ya kunu bayna hu
wa bayna ha illa zira'a
wa ya asbiqu alayhi al-kitab
wa ya amalu bi amali ahali al-jannah.
But look at it.
The prophet, sallallahu alayhi wa sallam,
when he told us in this hadith,
that individual has to do
amalu ahali al-jannah before dukhul al-jannah.
You can't get al-jannah with amalu ahali naar.
This is what we are talking about.
You want al-jannah bi amali ahali al-jannah.
You want Jahannam if you continue upon that.
If you continue upon the deeds of ahali naar,
it does not lead to anywhere but naar.
But as for the deeds of ahali al-jannah,
the individual has to switch
from the deeds of ahali naar
to the deeds of ahali al-jannah.
You do not get al-jannah
being upon the deeds of ahali naar.
May Allah protect all of us, depending on the sin
and depending on the way he will enter inside Jahannam.
And that was why the prophet Muhammad,
sallallahu alayhi wa alihi wa sallam,
in the last hadith that we read,
the hadith of Mu'adh ibn Jabal,
Mu'adh said, razi allahu anhu,
awsani rasulillahi sallallahu alayhi wa alihi wa sallam
afaqal, the messenger alayhi sallatu wa sallam
advised me and said,
la tu shirk billahi shay'a
ah Mu'adh, do not ever join partners
in anything with Allah,
subhanahu wa ta'ala
wa in ku tilta wa hurrikt
even if you are killed and burnt
avoid shirk
wa in ku tilta
wa hurrikt
even if you are killed and burnt
we explained in the last class
this is the best level of the people of Iman
otherwise if a person says something
man kafara billahi min ba'di imanihi
Allah told us about that in surat al-nahal
so illa man ukriha wa qalbuhu
mutma illum bil iman
so the one who was compelled
to have to say a thing of disbelief
if he says it
wa qalbuhu mutma illum bil iman
he said something upon disbelief
but his mind is settled
well grounded, tranquil upon Iman
this kind of a person is not upon a sin
but if he goes ahead
if you want to kill me, kill me
ash hadu an la ilaha illallah
wa ash hadu anna Muhammadan abduhu wa rasuluhu
this was the advice the prophet gave Mu'adh
sallallahu alaihi wa sallam
the second thing he said to him
he said
do not ever disobey or bring hearts to your parents
even if the two of them command you
to abandon your wife
that is divorce her
or to come away from your marriage
and your wealth
he said bring all your money to us
the ulama explained to us
it will be lawful to divorce a wife
or seek al-khol from a husband
upon the instruction of parents
if those parents are parents like Omar
or parents in the status of Iman
like Omar
parents who everything they do is upon Iman
and deen and good knowledge of Islam
as was Omar
or if it were parents who are non-talent
who are sinful
who are unrighteous far away from the sunnah
not to follow this instruction from them
would not constitute
it would not constitute disobedience to them
don't forget
that the prophet Muhammad sallallahu alaihi wa sallam
had said to us
that
may Allah protect us
there is no obedience to the created being
in disobedience to Allah sallallahu alaihi wa sallam
the first thing
the prophet sallallahu alaihi wa sallam
advice Mu'adh
was to stick to Iman
and not ever commit shirk
regarding any matter
the second advice is
don't ever
bring harm or hurt to your parents
or in Amaraka
even if
they command you
the two of them
to leave away your wife
or to come out of your marriage
and your wealth
except sallallahu alaihi wa sallam
don't ever ever
don't ever
abandon
any salah
that is
obligatory
knowingly
don't ever knowingly
abandon obligatory salah
because anyone who
deliberately
abandons an obligatory salah
forgot
the very admin who
such a person
the guarantee
of Allah
Allah's guarantee
Allah's protection over him is already removed
deliberately
abandoning salah
number four
don't taste anything
alcohol
don't taste it
in any form
in any quantity
don't taste alcohol
anything
that makes the individual
become unconscious
so it's not just talking about buying alcohol
the one we know
no, anything
so this means
every drug
every form of engagement in drug
don't deny it
in any form, in any quantity
the prophet said
because
whatever intoxicates
all that
intoxicates
it is
the head of every indecency
and obscenity
then he gave him the fifth
advice
beware, avoid
sinfulness
because sinfulness
makes
Allah's anger on you
lawful
it will invite it to you
it will create a path for it
Allah will be angry with you
when you are upon sinfulness
think about it
beware of it
avoid it
look in what
what do I do that is incongruent
with the instructions of Allah, avoid it
because that thing
will bring Allah's anger upon you
this one goes back to what
we started the class with
a person that begins to say he is upon sinfulness
but is expecting
goodness from Allah
the prophet told us
it brings and opens
the path
from Allah's anger to you
but here you are
you are waiting
for compassion, rahma and barakat
upon acts of sinfulness
meanwhile
the acts of sinfulness
will open a way of
Allah's anger against you
this is why the ulama
have mentioned, the one who is upon
sinfulness, expecting
goodness from Allah, has
some insanity with him
may Allah protect us
from all evils
al-Imam ibn al-Qayn went on
to say that
the reports, the ahadith from the prophet
sallallahu alaihi wa sallam
regarding things like this
they are
in the multitudes
of what
we have said
so it is not appropriate
for anyone who
loves himself and will be
sincere with himself
to close
his eyes away
from these reports
from these ahadith
and the warnings in them
and makes himself become
free
he eases up
inside sinfulness
and then
he begins
to think
and hope
in
positive anticipation
and good thoughts
you are upon sin
you ease up yourself
despite all these ahadith warning
warning warning warning
you go and start easing up
yourself in sinfulness
thinking that oh
I am thinking
positive about Allah
will Allah not show a messiah
upon me? but your deeds
are deeds of sinfulness
he said
was Ali ibn al-Qayn
well known from the scholars
of the madhab of
al-imam ahmad ibn al-hamman
abu al-wafa
Ali ibn al-Qayn
he said
rahimahullah he is well known
there is a book called al-funun
many students of knowledge would have
heard and read about this book
al-funun al-funun means
disciplines
the book discusses a lot of disciplines
it occurs in 400 volumes
it was reported
compiled by
abu al-wafa
Ali ibn al-Qayn
well known
he said
rahimahullah may Allah forgive him
be watchful regarding Allah
be watchful
be careful regarding Allah
regarding Allah
and don't
don't become deceived
that's Allah that
you want to forget yourself with
and deceive yourself with
you need to be very watchful
regarding your Lord subhanAllah
avoid disobeying
him
because this Allah you are seeing
subhanahu wa ta'ala
he ordered
subhanahu wa ta'ala that
the hand should be cut because of three dirhams
anyone who stole
three dirhams the messenger
the one who stole
something worth three dirhams the prophet
ordered that the hand should be cut
hand to be cut
for three dirhams
someone ordered that
should you not be careful about him
should you not
hold him
in esteem
should you take anything
flimsy with someone
who orders that
the one who stole
something worth three dirhams
the hand should be cut
so he said
rahimahullah
be watchful
be mindful
about Allah
and don't be deceived by yourself
so he cut the hand
in three dirhams
for three dirhams
he ordered that the hand
be cut
and the hand should be cut
in the head of the needle
Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala
legislated the hadj
punishment
in the head of the needle
regarding the head of the needle
when a person drinks it
from alcohol
the head of the needle
that is even a drop of it
he deliberately took it as an alcohol
he ordered that
such a person should be flogged
the prophet Muhammad
he had told us
man sharib al hamra fajlidu
anyone who drinks alcohol
flog him
so no matter
the size, no matter the
quantity, even if it be
the quantity of the tip of a needle
what quantity is that?
but he deliberately took it
and it is alcohol fajlidu
flog him
and we know the head of
sharib al hamra
forty strokes of the king
forty
some of the scholars even mention eighty
Omar was reported
to have given eighty
but most of them are up on forty
no matter the quantity
a lady got
Allah's anger
and she was punished
in the fire regarding
a cat
a lady was punished because
of a cat, we remember that hadith
the woman who
would tie
down and hold down her
cat, the prophet said
she would not provide
food for that cat
she would not also leave that
cat to go about
and find whatever it can eat
that cat died
out of hunger
someone out of
this kind of an attitude
towards a cat
Allah punished her with jahannam
meaning something people
we consider to be small
is big in the sight of Allah
someone stole three drinks
cut the hand
someone drank alcohol, give him forty strokes
of the king, someone tied
down a cat
punished the cat
till the cat died out of hunger
Allah punished her with jahannam
was a garment
they used to cover themselves up
with it
one of the companions during a battle
removed this
from the booty
before it was
shared
the person followed the prophet Muhammad
in that battle
and the person was killed
as a shaheed
this shamla
that he took
before it was distributed
it is from the aspects of
he took it
out of
public property
before it was distributed
the prophet told us
it will be
burnt in hell
despite the fact that
that person who took it
he died in that battle as a shaheed
so it was a small garment
it destroyed
a huge value
and made him became
exposed
to a big punishment from Allah
what he or she
would consider all mild
so is this
Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala
an individual who continues
on from big sins like
zina, like telling lies, like eating
riba, like disobedience to a parent
and then you are saying that
oh you are expecting
goodness from Allah rather than
turning a new leaf
so he said
this individual
is telling that
the shamla
became burnt with fire
upon the one who had taken
it out of the booty
and this was
a person who had been
but tired on the battlefield
ibn al-qayyim said
al-imam
al-imam also said
he also said that
al-imam
and
in all of these
the scholar said
he said
he saw the prophet
as a young person
but he never heard
any statement from him
usually the ulama
some of them count him as from
as from the
but this hadith
he said that the prophet
said
a man
because of a fly
became admitted
into aljannah
likewise
a man would enter jahannam
because of a fly
the companions asked
how will that happen because of a fly
someone got aljannah
because of a fly
someone got jahannam
how will that happen
explain to us o messenger of Allah
the prophet said
two men
passed by a group of people
they have an idol
that they worship
this idol
no one will pass by it
until you have sacrificed
and put forward something in sacrifice
for that idol
they said to one of these two men
who want to pass the idol
put something forward
for our god
for our idol
say look me i don't have something to give
they said to him
give
even if it be a fly
it's a point of benefit here
our brothers
who would contribute money
for ayah
look at what you are doing
compare it with the narration
the point in this hadith
you contribute to ayah
you contribute to ego
the Islam
as they call it
it does not prevent you from
participating in mass courage
and the worship around it
and the shirkiyat
that they commit
so our own deen prohibits it
this man
the first of them
he was asked
bring something
sometimes we are traveling
on the road
and we meet some people upon some shirk
and all that they say alaji give us money
don't give them
don't present anything
this one happens a lot
you are traveling say give us money
don't give it to them
don't give it
because giving it
will constitute
support for it
so this man
the prophet told us about the two of them
two men passed by a
community
the community
has an idol
they worship
no one would pass by
that community until
they had sacrificed something
for the idol
the community said to one of these two men
put forward something
the man said I don't have anything
to present to your
god
they said to him again
present something
even if it be a fly
this person
presented a fly
and they opened the way
for him to pass
the prophet said
this person
became from the people of the fire
he entered the fire
why?
what he did
is from the aspects of shirk
because our
Nusuk Allah told us
that it should be for Allah alone
they are for Allah alone
slaughtering is meant for Allah alone
so when he
killed a fly
for an idol it is from the aspects of
shirk
it is from the aspects of joining
partners with Allah
so what would he have done?
he would have just gone back
he could not pass
he turns his back away
so that was how the first
person got into jahannam
because of a fly
as for the second one
they said to him
present something, slaughter something
no matter how small
as for me
I will not in any way
present
or sacrifice anything
for anybody
aside Allah
subhanahu wa ta'ala
they cut the neck of this man and killed him
and he became from the people of aljannah
why has this imam
brought this hadith
he has brought this hadith
to make us understand that
Allah's punishment is severe
you cannot
commit the deeds of kufr
and expect
the rewards of the people of iman
likewise
Allah's mercy is vast
when you are
upon the deeds of iman
the deeds of taqwa
and ibadah
you should expect huge things from Allah
although the
ulama say this person who was killed
if he said
other than that
if he said other than what
he said that he would not
present to their lord
to their idol
what they request
just to be able to have his way
and pass away
while his heart is
established upon iman
it may be lawful for him to say
things like that
but the others amongst the ulama say he had
to stand firm
perhaps as a means of teaching
the rest of the people what exactly
iman is
or as a means of obtaining
the most lofty position
regarding the matters
like these
because perhaps in their own sharia
anyone who was compelled
to abandon iman
must not abandon
iman
different from what is in our own sharia
that anyone who was
upon real compulsion
genuine compulsion
that is real
he may say something
that may not be from the statements of
iman while his heart
is established upon
iman
they say this may not be like that
in their own sharia
that was why any sort of
compromise would make
the individual be from the people of
jahannam as we have
read in this hadith the point here is that
for the slightest
what the individual
called the slightest sacrifice
to other than Allah
it did not constitute
any other than shirk
and shirk brought the
mushrik the recompense
for shirk
shirk brought the mushrik
the ma'asia
brought the arsi
the recompense of
his ma'asia
the sinfulness brought
the sinful individual
the recompense for his
sinfulness
sinfulness will bring
the sinful person
the evil repercussions
of your sinfulness
sinfulness will
bring you the sinful
person the evil negative
repercussions of your sinfulness
just like
we read in the previous hadith
where the prophet said
that
sinfulness opens
the way for Allah's anger
that Allah's anger
against the sinful
is the evil repercussion of sinfulness
likewise
as we have read in this hadith
steadfastness upon goodness
steadfastness upon obedience
to Allah
steadfastness upon righteousness
will bring
the righteous individual
the good
the hope
the positive
the goodness that is connected
as rewards
for his goodness
so as the evil repercussions
who come to the one
who is upon evil
definitely
the rewards of
goodness will come
to the one who acts upon
goodness
the ulama al imam ibn al qaym also
said
this is also
just like
one statement
to one expression
that a person would make
that an
individual will make
just one statement
by the statements
he made
he will be dumped and hauled
in the fire
for a distance that is longer than the east
and the west, just one statement
the prophet said that to us
the individual will give
a statement, just one word you said
he does not really recognize
the evil repercussions of
what he has said
the evil repercussions of what you have said
will dump
the person in the fire
far much more than the distance
between the east and the west
this is to say that
don't underrate sinfulness
don't be upon sinfulness
while
hoping, sitting, waiting for
the recompense
of goodness
anyone who falls into sin should
repent, stop it
upon
the other leaf
al imam ibn al qaym continued
and said
after discussing
how
anticipating goodness
and good rewards
and good compassion
from Allah, this is what you are
waiting for
while you are upon sinfulness
another thing that makes people
remain upon sinfulness
is the fact that
they think that they have a lot of dunya with them
Allah has given
them a lot of money
Allah has given them the ability
to build a lot of houses
they have a lot of cars
they live in luxury
they rank
amongst the richest in the country
they are comfortable
they spend
as they desire
for them, that is a symbol
of goodness in this world
irrespective of the sins
that they may be upon
al imam ibn al qaym said
this is part of the
deceit of the shaytan upon these
individuals
perhaps
some of those in
self deceit
will depend upon
what he sees
from the tremendous
and
abundant
mercy of Allah upon him
in this dunya
tremendous, huge
covering everywhere
in terms of wealth
in this world that they have
so he makes
he is relaxed
say
some of those who are
upon self deceit
he begins to depend upon
on what he sees
what he can find
from the
farthest
profuse
mercy of Allah upon him in this dunya
he begins to feel safe
and say
this luxury that we have
this money that we have
this wealth that we have
this abundance that we have
these investments
that we have
these properties that we have
are
Allah will not
remove it from us
and that Allah will not have given him
such profuse wealth
except because of the love of Allah
upon him
he has a lot of money
he has a lot of wealth
in fact
he may hardly fall sick
because many times when we look at
the mercy of Allah
we don't look that
not falling sick is from that
mercy from Allah
many times people enjoy
sound health
and good wealth
many times people enjoy
sound health
and good wealth
and they begin to think like
Ibn al-Qayyim said to us
if you think
this wealth has not come to me
Allah has not
provided all these
mercies and luxury to him in this
dunya
except because
of the fact that Allah loves
me
oh Allah loves me
he gave me money
he gave me wealth
he gave me children
he gave me property
he gave me car, huge investments
a lot of gold, a lot of these
he begins to enjoy on all of these
he begins to think that inshallah
when we die
we are going to get even better than this
meanwhile he is up on riba
he is the chairman of riba based banks
the transactions he makes are up on riba
the investments that he sees blow some in
he took loans
of riba from various
banks
and he is waiting
he is up on zina when he likes
he forms musical concerts
he puts money
in various investments that are
unlawful, haram
but in this
world he is enjoying
he lives in big houses
he drives in big cars
security escorts
he drives in a private
jet
he goes left right
his children are in the best of schools across the world
what we will get in aljannah will be better than that
but his businesses are
from muharramats
he commits zina
he thinks yes, even if we do
Allah likes us
so he gives us all this money, may Allah
protect all of us
ibn al-qayyim said
this is
from the biggest
the most obnoxious
self-deceit
regarding Allah
if you are thinking about Allah
like this
perhaps one of those
in self-deceit will depend upon
he will be depending upon
what he has obtained
from the numerous messes
of Allah upon him in this dunya
and that Allah will not change all of these
luxuries that he has
provided him
and that Allah has not given him all these
worldly benefits, position
money, authority, property
except for the fact that Allah likes me
if Allah does not like me
he thinks that if Allah does not
like him
all these luxuries and comfort
ability to go everywhere
Paris, Brazil, Maldives
riding bicycles, everywhere
going everywhere
he has bought what billions on the seas
all these things they are from
the messes of Allah upon me
if not that Allah loves me
he will not give me all these
all these luxuries, yet
he is upon a river
he deals with river
he drinks haram
drinks alcohol
he commits zina
his investments are
in Muharramate, things that Allah
has prohibited
yet he has gathered a lot of luxury
and enjoys them thinking that Allah
loves him
he is even thinking
that Allah will provide him bigger
and better than that on the day of Qiyamah
in the hereafter
Al Imam said
this is from the most
obnoxious
self deceit regarding Allah
the one who thinks
Allah has given him a lot of money
Allah has given him
a lot of wealth
Allah has given him a lot of sound health
Allah has given him a lot of
servants and workers
companies, luxury
cars, planes, all of these
because Allah loves him
so he can continue upon his
sins, it will not change
when we enjoy this dunya we also enjoy
akhirah
this is from
the most
most
distasteful
self defeat
about Allah
you are really really deceiving yourself
regarding Allah
when you think that because of the wealth
that you enjoy
because of the comfort and luxury that you have
that means that Allah
loves you
so irrespective of your deeds
as long as you are luxurious
and comfortable
that means Allah loves you
there are a lot of people thinking like this
that when there is money what is left
when there is wealth
what is left, we have everything
I heard
one in a discussion
I read we were having
a discussion with someone who is
supposed to be learned
this person sees nothing wrong
in trading
in riba
he was arguing
in an argument he said something
he said if the
Europeans and the western world
if they deal in riba
yet we see
them in the opulence that we have
seen them, then it means
there is nothing wrong with the riba
this is what Ibn al Qaim said
rahimahullah
wa hadha min aqbahil gurur
billah, this is from the
most distasteful
did Allah not say to us that
do not be deceived
with the
thoughts and backwards of kufar
in luxury and comfort
in this dunya, don't be deceived by it
Allah said
what we have given them
is just a small enjoyment
for a small time
they will come back
they will end up inside Jahannam
so for anybody
to think that
the yardstick to show that Allah loves you
is that you have money
you are luxurious
big cars
fine clothes
sound health
a lot of children, big schools
laptop
big house
you fly all across the world
you have a visa
you have to go everywhere
that means Allah loves you
and then you do not go back
to look at your work
your deeds
is it upon haram
or halal
you don't care
as long as Allah has given you mercy
and favor
it means Allah loves us
al imam ibn al qaim
rahimahullah
wa hadha min aqbahil gurur
this is from the most
distasteful dishonoring
for you
to be thinking you are deceiving yourself
about Allah
our explanations
and further
discusses will be upon a man like this
the one we just ended
was a man who is upon sinfulness
and is thinking
hoping, waiting for goodness
from Allah
the other one is the one who is upon
worldly benefits and comfort
and luxury
he thinks that that is a sign that Allah loves him
irrespective of his
acts of unrighteousness and sinfulness
there are many people
who think like this
in fact today there are many parents who think like this
is this not the same thinking
of parents of boys who are upon yahoo
you think they have money
they have car
how did your son get to that
girls running about
in zina
men buy your children
your daughters iPhones
the mother is not asking
where did you get this phone from
my daughter
why she is not working anywhere
so many people think now that
once there is some worldly luxury
then there is goodness
oh there is
everything is okay
once the worldly benefits
the luxury
it appears comfortable
with sound health
don't worry the rest don't worry we sort it out
may Allah protect us
it is
said
from the most
deceitful
approach to self deceit
regarding Allah
is to think that because he gave you
money and luxury
that means that he loves you
absolutely no irrespective of
what you do no no no
by the will of Allah we will come into
fuller discussions regarding
these issues about the Rahman
can we have a few questions
the first
question
concerning
obedience to parents
if I had
sent my mother to
for being upright
but my father
ignores
sometimes
practice shirk
yet he sees that
I also sent him to her
what shall I do
the first thing you will do
oh
I congratulate
you
for what Allah has
provided you
regarding obedience
to him
and living
your life upon the Sunnah
and then bringing your
parents upon it beginning from
your mother and then
up to the level of
taking her for Hajj
may Allah accept it
from you
and forgive your mistakes
as for daddy
your dad who is remaining
is still delaying
or abandoning Salah
he may even get involved
in some deeds of shirk
please get close to him
find means
of talking to him
raise these matters
with him
help him be able to observe Salah
at its time
for example most times most of us
by the time of Maghrib and Isha
we are at home
from work
in fact from the time of Fajr
if you are not living in Lagos
you might not have left for your office
I understand that those of our
brothers in Lagos
some of them even before Fajr
they have left their home to be able
to arrive at work
to time
but those outside Lagos it is possible
for you and many others too
in Lagos
you will be at home for Salatul Fajr
for Salatul Maghrib
and Salatul Isha
one way to help your daddy
please be at home
go for those Salat
with him
be at home
go for Salatul Fajr with him
daddy let us go for
Salatul Fajr wake him up
in fact from the night
help him be able to
sleep early
so that waking up for Fajr
will not be of a burden
go with him
especially for Salatul Fajr
you might be at work
at Zuhr and Asr
but you can call him to ask daddy
it is time for Zuhr
have you observed Zuhr
or should I call one of my younger ones
to bring you water
are you going to the masjid
it will be a kind of a reminder
and pressure upon
goodness for him
to go for Salatul Zuhr
likewise for Salatul Asr
try to come back home before Maghrib
so that you go with him to the masjid
for Salatul Maghrib and Isha
these are clear cut practical means
in all of these
increase your
acts of goodness upon him
spending upon him
spending upon people
it eases
their mind
the mind of people
when people have hard heartedness
one of the means
that brings that down
is spending upon them well
so spend upon your daddy
he will have good
attention for you
and then by that
it will be easy for you to convince
him to drop those deeds
of shirk and stick
to Salat
after that take him for Hajj
in fact by the time you know
that you are able to stop his
acts of shirk
then you can start
preparing him to go for Hajj
expose him to lectures
many times many of us
we don't get our parents
exposed to good lectures
and we listen to
lectures every day every week
in fact in our vehicles
we are listening to lectures
please expose your parents to
your brothers to listening
to lectures
and participating in programs
because they will help
nurture
and grow your Iman
and theirs too
so expose daddy to lectures
especially those in Yoruba
if he is Yoruba speaking
expose him to lectures that discuss
the evils of going to
those who are fast
who mislead the people
expose him to lectures
talk to him to
spend on him
ensure to help him be able to go
for Salat
once he stops the shirk
pay for his Hajj
and start getting ready
to go with him for Hajj
while he corrects
other things and moves ahead
I hope that it is clear
these are clear cut practical steps
on what you have asked about
we beg Allah
to guide this
father of our brother asking this question
Allah guide him
Yaadul jalali wa ikram
Abaabu r-Rahman
As-Salaamu alaykum
Ameen wa Iyakum
Abaabu r-Rahman
Another question ready
Is it permissible for your wife to seek
divorce if important promises made
before marriage are reportedly
not fulfilled?
For example, if a husband
promised to abandon a particular
sin but continues
to return to it
There are two conversations
No, no, go
Despite more than ten years of marriage
and repeated efforts to resolve
the issue, would this be considered
a valid reason for seeking
divorce or should the woman
accept it as a part of
her brother or trials?
It depends
on the sin
It depends on the sin
If it's a sin of abandoning
Salaam
If it's a sin of eating riba
and bringing riba home for you
If it's a sin of being
up on 419 and other
sins of earnings
Yes, there are proper grounds
for you. I will even say ten years
is too much
In fact, you should not have gone
into that marriage until the
brother has stopped that sin
Don't joke with this matter
If a man is up on a sin
before he marries you
like going to
Afau Nijalabi
There are brothers who do it
May Allah protect all of us
Some people want protection
Some people want promotion
at job
That was what took them to Afau Nijalabi
And over last weekend
in Eloni
I heard one Afau Nijalabi
saying something. It was very strange
He says
The end
in the life of a person
up on Nijalabi will never be good
A person up on Nijalabi
will not end well. He said but he
is doing it
Subhanallah
If you have a man
doing this, he comes to propose
to you. That's enough reason for you to reject
A man is
working in a riba based bank
He comes to marry you
That's enough reason for you to reject
If a man is working
in a brewery and comes to marry you
would you accept the one
who eats riba, works
in a riba based bank is worse
than the person who works
in a brewery. Do you know that?
The sin of riba is worse
than the sin of alcohol
Riba is evil
Yet people go into society
My husband is working in this bank
My other husband is working in this bank
People who should be ashamed of themselves in public
amongst the Muslims
They are the ones who
when we do Muslim Ramadan
lecture, we invite chairman of
social bank. Let us stop these
Bank that is a
bank clearly known for riba
Riba is evil
So if a man is
upon all these kinds of sins
How come did you say yes to him
Were you not told to marry a man
who is righteous
So how come did you marry an unrighteous man
Many people think that just carry on
And what brings many to this
today now is luxury
Because he has money
Because he has a car
Because he has a big job
Because luxury took them to think
That the man will abandon the sin
He did not abandon the sin
Here you are
10 years after
You have eaten, you have slept, you go and go
Come back now, you are tired of it
This is the way of sinfulness
So I think you must be
more practical in your
approach to make him stop the sin
You know the sin, depending on the kind of sin
We are just giving examples
Be more practical
And be ready to leave the marriage if it is sins like
Zina
Zina is destructive
If it is things like going to see
Afon Nijalabi and all these
Especially if
things that do
with unlawful earning
It is from that unlawful earning
that he will bring to you to eat at home
It will affect you directly
and your children
So begin to negotiate
that you got into the marriage when you
manage upon things like this itself is wrong
So may Allah protect us
There is a second part of the question
which you started
A woman is giving conditions
before she gets into a marriage
If the condition is lawful
If a condition
is not a condition
that makes halal, haram
or that makes haram, halal
Then the man
accepts those conditions
The marriage is lawful
And it is lawful
For a man to accept that kind of a marriage
There is a condition
This condition is not changing halal
to haram
Neither is it changing haram to halal
Then it is lawful
And it is very necessary
for the man to fulfill it
Because the prophet told us about that
Alayhi Salatu Salam
From the strongest conditions a man must fulfill
must
are those
conditions by which
the women became lawful
for you to near them
So if at the beginning of the
Nikah you gave a
condition
Conditions are different from promises
You can just promise, we promise that
But it's a condition, I will not marry you
unless you agree to these things
These are different
They are stronger than just promising
It's just like promising good dealings
Promising this, promising that
Promises are strong in the Sharia
And from the ways of Munafikun
Is that
When he promises
He fails the promise
So promises are strong too
But these
When they occur as shurut
They are stronger
As conditions for marriage, they are stronger
So if you
Married a woman upon a condition
for marriage
Ensure that you fulfill it
If you don't fulfill it
She can conveniently
Approach the courts
And the marriage can be separated
It's a lawful
Means to seek
Separation from marriage
Conditions are violated
You go to the judge
Who will invite the man
You will prove your case
And the marriage will be dissolved
If you so want
So the matter is with the woman
If she likes
She can approach the court that the marriage
Should be separated
If she likes she can be patient
Even when the shurut were violated
But if they were promises
You can still be seeking
Begging, approach, making dua
And all of these
That the promises
Be fulfilled
I hope that it is clear
Allah is the greatest
God is the greatest
and you are with us
Allah is the greatest
As-Salaamu alaikum
Wa alaikum as-Salaam